<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eclectical chiliasm, or, A discourse concerning the state of things from the beginning of the Millennium to the end of the world</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E157A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171901</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09362333</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09362333</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42839</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42839)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1307:33 or 1792:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eclectical chiliasm, or, A discourse concerning the state of things from the beginning of the Millennium to the end of the world</title>
                  <author>T. F., 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 62, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author and sold by C. Brome at the Gun, at the west end of St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.F.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1792:20 identified as Wing E157B ("no entry" in Wing 2nd ed., 1994).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XX-XXI --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Millennium.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:1"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Eclectical Chiliaſm;</hi> OR, A DISCOURSE Concerning the State of THINGS FROM THE Beginning of the <hi>MILLENNIUM</hi> To the end of the WORLD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and Sold by <hi>C. Brome</hi> at the Gun, at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>Thomas Barnardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſton</hi> Baronet</head>
            <p>THIS Diſcourſe is humbly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>by T. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have here attempted an Expoſition of the Prophetick Viſions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Twentieth and One and Twentieth Chapters of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> A Book which on pretence of its Myſteriouſneſs is too much neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This as well as the reſt of the Bible was undoubtedly Written for our Learning; and to encourage our Induſtry and Study, a Bleſſing is promiſed to them that Read, and Hear, and Keep the Words of this Prophecy, and the things which are Written therein, Chap. 1. 3. which ſuppoſeth that the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:42839:4"/> of theſe Myſteries is attainable. I am far from pretending to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all the Viſions of this Obſcure and Myſterious Book. Nay, I dare not boaſt of an intimate and thorough Acquaintance with thoſe I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to explain. Yet I hope I am not a perfect Stranger to them, nor wholly miſtaken in the meaning of any One Viſion. I know they are differently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by the Learned <hi>Hammond, Grotius,</hi> and other Modern Expoſitors. But their way of interpreting has been ſolidly evinced to be none of the beſt, by the Learned Author of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Godlineſs, ſo that my hopes are not much ſhaken with the Authority of theſe great Men. As to what concerns the Subject of the following Diſcourſe, the <hi>Millennium</hi> is by them made to begin at <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> which is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb facs="tcp:42839:4"/> confuted by the State of things from that <hi>Epocha</hi> to the end of the Thouſand Years. And conſequently all Interpretations purſuant to that Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis fall to the ground. Beſides, how unſatisfactory is their Expoſition of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and what little affinity between the Viſion and the Event that is applied to it? For <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> come from the Four Quarters of the Earth, and periſh in their attempt againſt the Camp of the Saints and the beloved City. But the <hi>Turks</hi> came only from the North Parts, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in their Enterprize against the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> took <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and have been in Poſſeſſion of it very near Two Hundred and Fifty Years. But I decline this invidious Argument, and for the Readers better ſatisfaction ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:42839:5"/> acquaint him with the grounds on which I proceed.</p>
            <p>The Hypotheſis to which my Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is framed, is that of the Learned Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> which has been fully vindicated by Dr. <hi>Hen. More</hi> in his Book even now mentioned. The Viſions I diſpoſe agreeably to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Time in which they are fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And having framed my Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the most obvious ſenſe of the words, I conſider whether the ſuppoſed Event hath been foretold by any Prophetick Writer. And upon En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry I find a moſt wonderful agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between theſe Viſions, and ſeveral Prophecies in the Old Teſtament. And if any of them ſeem to relate to things already paſt, and to have received their accompliſhment, this doth not hinder
<pb facs="tcp:42839:5"/> the accommodation of them to the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennial Reign; For the ſame Prophecy may very well reſpect different and far diſtant events, of which ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances might be given. But I am perſwaded moſt of theſe Prophecies were never yet fulfill'd, particularly thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the peaceable State of Chriſt's Kingdom, the Return and Incorporation of the Twelve Tribes, the Army of <hi>Gog,</hi> and that we are yet to expect the. Accompliſhment of them in the last Times of the World. But I am not much concerned what become of this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion.</p>
            <p>For if this ſupport from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of the Prophets fail, the whole Fabrick of my Expoſition will ſtand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken, being grounded upon the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
<pb facs="tcp:42839:6"/> meaning of the Viſions, confirmed and ſtrengthened by expreſs Texts of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> and very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Reaſons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Eclectical Chiliaſm;</hi> OR, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the State of Things from the Beginning of the</hi> Millennium <hi>to the end of the World.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>THE moſt Judicious Expoſitor of the Revelation is the eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Learned Mr. <hi>Joſeph Mede</hi> of Pious Memory, to whoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours next to Divine Aſſiſtance, the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der knowledge I have in Prophetick My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries is chiefly owing. His Method of interpreting the Apocalyptick Viſions is grounded on his Scheme of Synchroniſms, that moſt happy diſcovery and only ſafe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42839:7"/> Rule of Interpretation; <q>and muſt be acknowledged to be the moſt natural and unconſtrained, moſt agreeable to the ſtyle of the Prophets, and likewiſe to Hiſtory and Event.</q> His large Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary on the Apocalypſe ends with Ch. 14. On the reſt he has only publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſome ſhort Specimens or Eſſays, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending as the Writer of his Life tells us, to go over them again, and then to perfect his thoughts, and as fully to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large himſelf upon them as he had done upon the foregoing Chapters. Beſides, his Eſſay on Ch. 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contains ſome peculiar Sentiments, which even among his greateſt Friends and Admirers have not found equal acceptance with the reſt of his elaborate Commentary. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of theſe Notions is very pleaſing and ſurprizing. How learnedly does he expound the Prophecy of St. Peter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Day of Chriſt's ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in favour of his Opinion of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration and Renovation of the World? His conceit of the great Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and of the Reign of the Saints on Earth is not without ſome fair probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. How ingenious is his Conjecture of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42839:7"/> 
                  <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog?</hi> And there is an agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Beauty of thought in his diſtinction of the ſtate of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the ſtate of the Nations which ſhall walk in the light thereof. And yet I do not find that he hath made many Proſelytes to his perſwaſion concerning theſe Points. As touching the Viſions relating to theſe Myſteries they are in my opinion capable of a more ſatisfactory Expoſition, which is here attemped. I ſhall diſcourſe them in the ſame order they are accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>To the Millennial ſtate belong,</p>
               <p>Firſt, The binding and confinement of Satan.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Reſurrection and Reign of the Saints.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The new Heavens and the new Earth.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The thouſand years expired' <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> invade the Camp of the Saints.</p>
               <p>And to this Expedition ſucceeds, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Judgment and End of the World.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42839:8"/>
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of</hi> Satan<hi>'s Confinement.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE preparation to the Millennial happineſs is the binding the Devil and ſhutting him up in the bottomleſs pit. ch. 20. 1, 2, 3. I ſaw an Angel come down from heaven, having the key of the bottomleſs pit, and a great Chain in his Hand. And he laid hold on the Dragon that old Serpent, which is the Devil and Satan, and bound him a thouſand years, and caſt him into the bottomleſs pit, and ſhut him up, and ſet a ſeal upon him, that he ſhould deceive the Nations no more, till the thouſand years ſhould be fulfilled. All which ſignifies no more than the cloſe reſtraint of the Devil, and the retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that liberty which hitherto for wiſe ends God is pleaſed to indulge him. Now he is permitted to go to and fro in the Earth and to walk up and down in it, <hi>Job</hi> 1. 7. to practiſe his Infernal devices and arts of deceit. But then he ſhall be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42839:8"/> confined to the aery Regions his proper Territories; or his walk on the Earth ſhall be limited to a narrower compaſs, viz, the nations not converted to the Faith of Chriſt. 'Tis ſaid ver. 7. 8. that <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil being looſed out of Priſon, goes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the nations in the four quarters of the Earth, and to gather them together to Battel,</hi> which ſeems to imply, that the Heathen nations during the term of his confinement ſhall not be expoſed to his deceitful practices. Which if true, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to the Pagan World a great freedom from the miſeries and calamities of war. But whatever liberty the Devil may have in other parts, he ſhall be wholly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Nations walking in the light of the new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> To which excluſion will be conſequent a great encreaſe of of Peace, Truth and Piety in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As for wars and publick quarrels, Satan without queſtion hath a principal Hand in them. The great battel at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageddon</hi> is undertaken at the inſtigation of unclean Spirits, <hi>which go forth unto</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42839:9"/> 
                     <hi>the Kings of the Earth, to gather them to the battel of the great day of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Rev. 16. 14. And no ſooner is the Devil let looſe, but we find him at his old Employment, gathering the Nations to battel againſt the Saints ch. 20. 7, 8. Hence, without contradicting St. <hi>James,</hi> come Wars and Fightings, Quarrels and Diſſenſions. For even the luſts and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, to which the Apoſtle intitles them, are excited and enraged by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the profeſſed enemy to Peace and Unity. Peace as is obſerved by a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man, is the peculiar character of Man, as he is diſtinguiſhed from Brutes. And the great deſign of the Goſpel is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this diſpoſition, and to inſpire the World with a Spirit of univerſal love and Charity. When therefore the Devil ſhall be under cloſe reſtraint, and Men left to the Bent of their own inclinations, and the Conduct of Religion, there will doubtleſs be greater Friendſhip &amp; Concord in the World both among particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and public Societies. And ſuch a peaceable State the Prophets foretell as the peculiar happineſs of the Kingdom of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42839:9"/> Chriſt. For thus it was propheſied by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> that under his government <hi>Men ſhall beat their Swords into plow-ſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-hooks;</hi> that Nation ſhall not lift up Sword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn War any more. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 4. And we meet with the ſame Prophecy in <hi>Micah</hi> with this addition, <hi>They ſhall ſit every Man under his Vine and under his Fig-tree, and none ſhall make them afraid.</hi> Chap. 4. 3, 4. Hitherto hath been a perfect Reverſe of all this. Men have beat their Plowſhares in Swords, and their pruning Hooks into Spears. The Art of War was never more ſtudied. And very frequent interruptions have been given to Mens ſecurity by rumors of Wars, and hoſtile Invaſions which hath furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Jews</hi> with a very plauſible Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the truth of our Bleſſed Saviours pretences. But theſe glorious Prophecies concern the Reign of Chriſt under the Millennial ſtate, and ſhall then have their accompliſhment. When Satan that grand Incendiary whoſe buſineſs and delight it is to diſturb the peace of mankind, ſhall be Chained up; then the Peace of God,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42839:10"/> that Divine grace of peaceableneſs to which we are called by the preaching of the Goſpel, ſhall more univerſally bear Rule in the Hearts of Men, and tune the World to a bleſſed Harmony.</p>
                  <p>This peace in the ſtate will be attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with peace in the Church, which ſhall enjoy a happy Calm, free on the one hand from the violences of Perſecution, and on the other from the diſturbances of falſe Teachers. The Names of Perſecutors are diſtinguiſhed in ſtory by peculiar Marks and Characters of Infamy. But the grand Perſecutor, the Devil, is not ſo common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken notice of. 'Tis certain from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that he is concerned, as Principal, in all the Perſecutions that have been raiſed againſt the Church of Chriſt. Thus the Chriſtians of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> who ſuffered Impriſonment in the cauſe of Religion, are ſaid to be <hi>caſt into Priſon by the Devil,</hi> Rev. 2. 20. And ch. 12. 4. We find the red Dragon waiting the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of the Starry-crowned Woman with an intention to devour her Child, that is the Devil inſtigating the Heathen
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42839:10"/> Emperors to extinguiſh and deſtroy the Apoſtolic Church, and to ſuppreſs Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianity at its Firſt appearance. And when the Woman fled into the Wilderneſs, the Dragon purſues her, and by the aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Beaſt with ſeven Heads and Ten Horns, to whom he committed his Power and authority, makes War with the remnant of her ſeed that refuſed to receive the Mark of the Beaſt, viz, the ſincere profeſſors of the Goſpel. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>human Cruelties exerciſed by theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, whether Heathen or Chriſtian or rather Antichriſtian, ſhew whoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents they were, and by what Spirit they were acted. 'Twas the red Dragon that inſpired them with ſuch Bloody and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous minds, and prompted them to thoſe outrages and violences ſo contrary to that kindneſs and compaſſion, which is one of the prime and eſſential inclinations of Mankind. And therefore when this cruel Fiend, who thus depraves the mild Tempers of Men, and inflames their minds to ſuch cruelty and fierceneſs, ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to the bottomleſs pit; and human nature left to the conduct of its own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42839:11"/> cultivatad and improved with the mild and merciful principles of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion, the Church ſhall no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be aſſaulted with ſtorms of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but be Bleſſed with a moſt profound tranquility. And What thus with great reaſon is infer'd from the premiſes, may with greater certainty be deduced from the predictions of the Prophets. For this ſtate of Freedom from Sufferings <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſies of. ch. 25. 8. <hi>He will ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up Death in Victory, and the Lord God will wipe away Tears from off all Faces.</hi> With which agrees St. <hi>Johns</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the ſtate of the new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Rev. 21. 4. <hi>God ſhall wipe away all Tears from their Eyes; and there ſhall be no more Death, neither Sorrow, nor crying neither ſhall there be any more pain for the former things are paſſed away.</hi> Which does not Signifie that Men ſhall be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and no longer obnoxious to Sickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and bodily Pains, but only that the Church ſhall enjoy a happy ſecurity from the calamities and ſufferings of former times. Secondly, The Peace of the Church is not a little diſturbed by the intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42839:11"/> Zeal of falſe Teachers. By whom theſe <hi>Seducers</hi> that divide the Church into Sects and Parties are ſent out and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we learn from our Saviours explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parable of the Tares, Matt 13. 37, 38, 39. <hi>He that ſoweth the good ſeed is the Son of Man. The field is the World, the good ſeed are the Children of the Kingdom, but the tares are the Children of the wicked One. The enemy that ſowed them is the Devil.</hi> Whence it appears that 'tis the Devil that ſows theſe tares of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retics and Schiſmatics that overrun the field of the Church, and infuſes into their minds falſe and corrupt doctrines. And thus that Floud of Arrianiſm that well nigh overwhelmed the Primitive Church is ſaid to have proceeded out of the mouth of the old Serpent, Rev. 12. 15. And the Corruption of the Chriſtian faith in the latter times is attributed to the Devil by the Apoſtle, Tim. 4. 1. In the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spirits and doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of Devils, that is doctrines Suggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Evil Spirits. So that when the Devil ſhall be reſtrained from ſowing his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42839:12"/> tares, and corrupting the minds of Men with falſe notions of things; there will doubtleſs follow greater conſent in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, Truth will prevail and Flouriſh, and bear down all oppoſite Errors, which will find no patrons to maintain and propagate them. This Concluſion is grounded not only on reaſon, but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy. For this <hi>Zechary</hi> propheſied ſhould come to paſs in the days of the Meſſias. ch. 13. 2. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs in that day, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, that I will cut off the names of the Idols out of the land, and they ſhall no more be remembred: And alſo I will cauſe the prophets, viz, that ſpeak lies, and the unclean Spirit to paſs out of the Land.</hi> Satan hath had his Miniſters, falſe Teachers, in every age of the Church, but the time will come when theſe lying Prophets ſhall ceaſe and be removed out of it. <hi>They ſhall have no place in the new Jeruſalem. For out of it ſhall be excluded them that make a lie. Rev.</hi> 21. 27. And ſuch are falſe Apoſtles, thoſe deceitful workers that transform themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and with fair ſpeeches deceive the Hearts of the Simple.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42839:12"/> II. A great encreaſe of Piety will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this confinement of Satan. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Goſpel is to reſtrain Men from all impiety, and to oblige them to the practice of univerſal goodneſs. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the nature of the laws the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel preſcribes, their agreeableneſs to the beſt reaſon of mankind, and their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to promote both our eternal and temporal happineſs, 'tis ſtrange Mens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are not more conformable to them. It is true human nature by the Fall of our firſt Parents is very much corrupted, and tainted with evil Inclinations. And this inbred Corruption doth at once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſe us to Goodneſs, and betray us to many ſinful practices agreeable to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved appetites. But I cannot think Men would arrive at ſuch heights of wickedneſs and villainy as we ſee many do, unleſs they were puſht forward by the Inſtigation of ſome wicked Spirits, who as the Scripture tells us work in, act and inſpire the Children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, great and notorious Sinners over whom they have a more immediate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42839:13"/> and power. Eph. 2. 2. Nor is the Devil wanting to inſnare and allure even good Men into forbidden courſes. Hence he hath the title of the Tempter, becauſe he makes it his great buſineſs and employment to ſeduce Men to Sin. So that the greateſt part of the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that is committed in the World is owing to the Temptations of evil Spirits, who by preſenting to Men the oppertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and occaſions of ſin, and infuſing into them evil motions excite and actuate that Corruption which is inherent in our nature. When therefore the Devil ſhall be ſhut up in the Abyſſe, and reſtrained from tempting Men, without doubt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality and wickedneſs will decline, and there will be a general and more exact conformity to the dictates of Reaſon and the laws of Religion. And this flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate of Religion is clear from expreſs texts of Scripture. For thus Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſaid to dwell in the new Heavens and new Earth 2 Pet. 3. 13. <hi>And</hi> St. <hi>John ſaith that nothing that defileth ſhall enter into the new Jeruſalem.</hi> Rev, 21.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42839:13"/> 27. Which plainly ſignifies a great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Piety and Vertue in the Millennial State of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42839:14"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Reſurrection and Reign of the Saints.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I <hi>Saw Thrones and they ſat upon them; and judgment was given unto them; And I ſaw the Souls of them that were beheaded for the witneſs of Jeſus, and for the word of God, and which had not Worſhipped the Beaſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Image, neither had received his Mark upon their foreheads, or in their hands; and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years.</hi> Rev 20. 4. <hi>But the reſt of the dead lived not again until the thouſand years were finiſhed. This is the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Bleſſed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt Reſurrection: On ſuch the ſecond Death hath no power.</hi> ver, 5. 6. Here are two things to be conſidered. 1 The judgment given to them that ſat on Thrones. 2 The Living of the Beheaded and their reigning with Chriſt, The meaning of the Firſt is clear from a paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42839:14"/> place <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 22. Judgment was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Saints of the moſt High. That both the One and the Other belong to the ſame thing is evident, becauſe they begin from the ſame Term, viz, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the fourth Beaſt, That in <hi>Daniel, when the Beaſt (then ruling in the wicked Horn) was ſlain, and his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſtroyed and given to the burning flame,</hi> ver 11, 21, 22. This in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calypſe, <hi>when the Beaſt and the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet (the wicked Horn in Daniel) were taken and both caſt alive into a lake of Fire burning with Brimſtone,</hi> Rev. 19. 20, 21, &amp;c. vid Mede Ep. 15, They there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw ſitting on Thrones are the <hi>Saints</hi> of the moſt High, that is the <hi>Jews,</hi> the holy People as they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 24. 12. 7. <hi>And to them Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was given i. e.</hi> Dominion or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. For ſo it follows in the place even now, cited, <hi>The Saints poſſeſſed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> ch. 7. 22. When the Courſe of the four Monarchies is finiſhed by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Fourth Beaſt, the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled. <hi>And from thenceforth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ngdom and Dominion</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:42839:15"/> 
                     <hi>and greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven ſhall be given to the People of the Saints of the moſt High,</hi> Daniel 7. 27. And thus of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>That the Kings of the Earth do bring their Glory and Honour into it</hi> Rev. 21. 24. Of this ſee a more ful and particular account in the fourth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>As for the other part of this viſion, I find no Key to it in the Prophets. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect whereof I think it ſafeſt to attend to the plain literal ſenſe of the words. And if it be interpreted by this Rule, the thing ſignified muſt be the Reſurrection and Reign of the Martyrs.</p>
                  <p>The Reſurrection of the dead is a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Article of Chriſtian Faith, built on clear and expreſs texts of Scripture. But in what order the dead ſhall be raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is no where expreſly declared. This only we learn from St. <hi>Paul</hi> that the Good and the Wicked ſhall not ariſe at the ſame Inſtant, but that the Righteous will have the Precedency. 1 Cor. 15. 23. <hi>Every</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42839:15"/> 
                     <hi>Man in his own order. Chriſt the firſt Fruits, afterward they that are Chriſts, at his Coming.</hi> Agreeable to this is that of the ſame Apoſtle 1 Theſ 4. 13. The Lord himſelf ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, and with the voice of the Arch-angel and with the Trump of God, and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt. Now a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Martyrs prior to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reſurrection is very conſiſtent with theſe aſſertions of the Apoſtle, which do not deny the Reſurrection of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons before the Coming of Chriſt to judgment, but only declare that Such of the Righteous whom Chriſt at his coming ſhall find in the ſtate of the dead ſhall have the Precedency of the wicked, and be firſt reſtored to life. St. <hi>Matthew</hi> tells us, that at our Saviours Reſurrection <hi>the graves were opened, and many Bodies of Saints which ſlept aroſe and went into the holy City, and appeared unto many.</hi> ch 27. 52, 53. And why may not the Privilege of a more early Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection be indulged the Martyrs in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their Sufferings? The invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Courage and Reſolution of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42839:16"/> Chriſtians proceeded in a great meaſure from the hope and expectation of it. And perhaps the Revelation of ſuch a diſtinguiſhing Favour was deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on purpoſe for the encouragement and ſupport of their Conſtancy under thoſe Perſecutions wherewith God thought fit to exerciſe the Faith and Patience of the firſt Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>That the Martyrs after their Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſhall Reign on Earth is an opinion which hath no countenance from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. All St. <hi>John</hi> here ſaith is, <hi>that the Beheaded lived again and reigned with Chriſt a Thouſand Years,</hi> which does not at all favour this Conceit, but rather ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the contrary. The Dominion Chriſt was inveſted with at his Aſcenſion, he is to poſſeſs to the end of the World. There is no new Kingdom to be erected for him upon Earth, nor will he deſcend from Heaven where he now reigns un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the time appointed by God for the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World. Then he will ariſe from his Imperial Seat at his Fathers right Hand, and come down into theſe lower
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42839:16"/> Regions in order to the holding his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſizes. And this is the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding act, and will put an end to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reign. Now if the Martyrs ſhall be admitted to a participation of Chriſts Kingdom, where ſhould they reign but in Heaven, where Chriſts Throne is, where he reigns in Perſon and from whence he adminiſters all the affairs of the World. There is nothing of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox in this Suppoſition to them who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Principles and Doctrines of Chriſtianity, which teach that the bodies of good Men being raiſed out of the duſt, and faſhioned like unto Chriſts glorious Body, ſhall be tranſlated from this Earth to the Manſions prepared for them in the Heavens. And So far is this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of the Millennial Reign from contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any text of Scripture, that it ſeems to have a good foundation in it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 One principal act of Regality is the power of judging Now St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us <hi>that the Saints ſhall judg the World</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. Which to be underſtood of the laſt and final judgment the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42839:17"/> verſe does clearly evince. Know ye not that we ſhall judge Angels? That is, ſuch of them as for their Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God were condemn'd to Hell, and are <hi>reſerved in Chains unto the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great day,</hi> Jude ver. 6. Which is the only judgment to which they are deſtined. The judgment therefore of the World by the <hi>Saints</hi> is no other than that at the laſt day. But who are the <hi>Saints</hi> to whom this autority and power is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? Not the Righteous in general, for they as well as the wicked muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the judgment ſeat is Chriſt to give an account If their actions. But perhaps when their Trial is finiſhed, and the Sentence of Abſolution pronounced, they ſhall be tranſlated into the Air, and being placed on Thrones around the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal of Chriſt, ſhall bear a part as Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors in the enſuing judgment of Devils and wicked men. But our Saviours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Proceſs of the laſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intimates the contrary. For the ſheep and the goats receive their different Sentences, whileſt they are ſtanding the one at the Right, the other on the left
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42839:17"/> Hand of the Judge. Matt 25. 34. <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on his right Hand Come ye Bleſſed of my Father inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World,</hi> But to them on the left <hi>Depart ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire.</hi> ver, 41. Whence it appears that the Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Righteous into the Clouds of Heaven 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 17. muſt Succeed the trial of the wicked, and conſequently they cannot be concerned in judging them. The <hi>Saints</hi> therefore by whom the World of the ungodly ſhall be judged, and in all probability the Martyrs who reigning with Chriſt in his Kingdom, will joyn with him in the exerciſe of his judiciary autority, and give their ſuffrages to the Sentence which he will paſs upon the wicked. This Solemnity 'tis true is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted after the Thouſand years allotted for the Martyrs Reign are expired, which ſeems to exclude them from bearing any part in this Regal act of judging the World. But there is no neceſſity of concluding their reign with this term, which may very well be extended to the end of Chriſts Mediatorial Kingdom. But becauſe the intermediate ſpace from this period to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42839:18"/> the final judgment is but ſhort Rev 20. 3. therefore the duration of their Reign is expreſſed by the complete number of a Thouſand years, the odd years that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not being brought into the account.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beſides the glorious Angels, we read of Myriads of <hi>Saints</hi> that accompany Chriſt in his triumphant progreſs from Heaven, <hi>Jude,</hi> ver 14. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 13. To under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this of Angels is without reaſon to depart from the letter of Scripture againſt the generally received rule of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But to apply it to the Souls of juſt Men is much more abſurd. For theſe are diſpoſed in Paradiſe or <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſom till the Reſurrection. Then being reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Bodies they appear before the judgment Seat of Chriſt, and being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally abſolved attend the judge in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to Heaven. And are now firſt of all admitted into the immediate preſence of God, where there is fulneſs of joy and perfection of happineſs. To ſend good Men directly to Heaven when they die, and to fetch them from thence at the laſt day to be judged, that after judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42839:18"/> they may return to their former happy ſeats with the greater Solemnity, is ſuch an odd prepoſterous method of proceeding as no conſidering Man will eaſily admit, much leſs believe agreeable to the infinite wiſdom of Almighty God. Whereas if a firſt and particular Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection be ſuppoſed, a good account may be given of the forementioned texts. For then the <hi>Saints</hi> that come with Chriſt will be thoſe holy Perſons who for their conſtancy in Suffering Death for the ſake of God, were Honoured with the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar favour of a more early admiſſion into the Kingdom of Heaven. Thus this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Millennial Reign of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs is not without ſome fair appearance of probability, and is very agreeable to the Goſpel Oeconomy.</p>
                  <p>If a figurative Interpretation were to be admitted, the Living of the Beheaded and their reigning with Chriſt a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years would ſignifie the Riſing of the Church from a dead eſtate, and its enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of peace and tranquility, to which ſence moſt, that I meet with, incline, But
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42839:19"/> this notion of a Metaphorical Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is encumbred with ſeveral difficulties which I cannot overcome, For Firſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that hath part in this firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is pronounced Bleſſed and holy and ſecure from the Power of the ſecond Death, that is, the miſeries of the other World. But ſhall every member of the Church in the Millennial State be eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſed? Secondly, The ſtate of the Church before the Millennium ſhall be very quiet and peaceable in reference to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and perſecution. For the Beaſts Power of making war with the <hi>Saints</hi> is contemporary with the mournful Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the two Witneſſes, which ends with the ſixth Trumpet. And the laſt act of hoſtility committed by the Beaſt will be the ſlaughter of the witneſſes, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive and are exalted on high before the ſeventh Angel ſounded. Rev. 11. 11, 12. And from that time to the final deſtruction of the Beaſt under the ſeventh Vial, the Saints will live ſecure from the violence of Perſecution. To underſtand therefore the firſt Reſurrection of the riſing of the Church from an oppreſſed and perſecuted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42839:19"/> ſtate is not agreeable to the condition of the times immediately preceding. Theſe and ſome other reaſons prevail with me to reject this opinion, and to interpret this viſion according to the proper mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42839:20"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the New Heaven and the New Earth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AND I ſaw a New Heaven and a New Earth, for the firſt Heaven and the firſt Earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea,</hi> Rev. 21. 1. The Viſion of a New World immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that of the general Judgment, ſeems to ſignifie the Production of a new and more glorious Earth, after the Deſtruction of the old by Fire, for the Seat and Habitation of the Bleſſed. But this is a Myſtery paſt my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. All that is ſignified by it is a more flouriſhing and proſperous State of things. In the Prophetick Style great Changes are expreſſed by a New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a New Earth, which in the Language of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſignifies a new World, and was uſed by them according to the preſent Notion of it among us,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42839:20"/> to denote a new Face and Condition of Things. This new Creation God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chap. 65. 17. <hi>Behold I create new Heavens and a new Earth, and the former ſhall not be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, nor come into mind.</hi> What follows in that Chapter does unfold the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Creation. <hi>Be you glad and rejoyce in that which I create, for behold I create Jeruſalem a rejoycing and her Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a joy,</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>And I will rejoyce in Jeruſalem and joy in my People, and the voice of weeping ſhall be no more heard in her, nor the voice of crying,</hi> verſ. 19. <hi>They ſhall build Houſes and inhabit them, and they ſhall plant Vineyards, and eat the fruit of them,</hi> verſ. 21. <hi>The Wolf and the Lamb ſhall feed together, and the Lion ſhall eat Straw like the Bullock, and Duſt ſhall be the Serpents Meat. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my Holy Mountain, ſaith the Lord,</hi> verſ. 25. This Mountain is the Church or Kingdom of Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. And the joyful, ſecure, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able condition of it, is that New Heaven and Earth which God promiſes to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. This new World, this happy State
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42839:21"/> of the Church hath not yet been ſeen. <hi>Nevertheleſs we according to this promiſe look for New Heavens and a New Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Peter 3. 13. In the fore-going Verſes St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of the melting of the Elements, of the burning of the Earth, and the Diſſolution of all things. And then it follows, <hi>nevertheleſs we according to his Promiſe look for New Heavens and a New Earth.</hi> Whence ſome have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that this New World muſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Conflagration, which is a great miſtake. For St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s New Heaven and Earth is no other than that promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65. 17. And the New World in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth clearly belong to the Kingdom of Chriſt, which muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Reſurrection and laſt Judgment, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. 25, 26, 28. <hi>He muſt Reign till he hath put all Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies under his Feet. The laſt Enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed is Death. And when all things ſhall be ſubdued unto him then ſhall the Son alſo himſelf be ſubject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.</hi> If therefore
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42839:21"/> the New Heaven and New Earth muſt be before the Concluſion and Surrender of Chriſt's Kingdom, then muſt it of neceſſity be before the Conflagration of the World, which will not begin, 'till the Judgment is concluded. And though there are no certain Characters in the Revelation, by which the preciſe time of this Viſion may be found out; yet from that place in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> it may be concluded to belong to the Kingdom of Chriſt, and particularly to the laſt Scene of it under the <hi>Millennium,</hi> when the State of Things will be vaſtly different from what they are or have hitherto been, as has been fully proved in the firſt Chapter. And ſo great will be the proſperity of the Millennial State, that there will be no longer need of Ships for War or Foreign Commerce and Traffick, which the preſent condition of things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, which I take to be the meaning of what is added by St. <hi>John, and there was no more Sea.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:42839:22"/>
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the new Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I John ſaw the holy City, the New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem coming down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her Huſband. And I heard a great voice out of Heaven, ſaying, behold the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of God is with Men, and He will dwell with them, and they ſhall be His People, and God himſelf ſhall be with them and be their God.</hi> Rev 21. 2, 3, Concerning the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> here are three things to be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. What is meant, 1 By the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi> 2 By its coming down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. 3. By the walking of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the light of it, ver. 21. Theſe I take to be the moſt material Points, the reſolution whereof will give us a clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this Myſtery.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>By the New Jeruſalem or the Lambs Wife</hi> ver, 9, 10. Is meant the People of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42839:22"/> the <hi>Jews</hi> converted to the Faith of Chriſt. Upon the ruin of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Elders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce for the approaching ſolemnity of the Lambs Marriage. Rev 19. 7. <hi>Let us be glad and rejoyce for the Marriage of the Lamb is come, and his Wife hath made her ſelf ready.</hi> Now the fall of <hi>Babylon</hi> and deſtruction of the ſeven-headed Beaſt, or Roman Empire, is the very point of time prefixt for the Converſion and Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, That their blindneſs and infidelity ſhall then be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, we learn from St. <hi>Paul</hi> Rom. 11. 25. <hi>I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant of this Myſtery, that blindneſs in part is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to Iſrael, until the fulneſs of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles be come in, And ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> This coming in of the fulneſs of the Gentiles, is of the ſame Import and Significancy, with the fulfilling the times of the Gentiles, which puts an end to the Miſeries and diſperſions of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Luk. 21. 24. <hi>And they ſhall fall by the Edge of the Sword, and ſhall be lead away captive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Nations, and Jeruſalem ſhall be troden down of the Gentiles, until the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled.</hi> The times of the Gentiles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42839:23"/> are the times of the four Monarchies, wherein the Gentiles have dominion. And when the time of the fourth and laſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy is expired and accompliſhed, the <hi>Jews</hi> will every where embrace the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion, and be reſtored to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Countrey from which they have ſo long been baniſhed. Now if the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Lamb are co-incident and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen at the ſame time, what can we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Bride, the Lambs Wife to be, but the <hi>Jews,</hi> once Gods peculiar people, to whom after ſo long a divorce he will be graciouſly recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, and receive them again into favour. The greatneſs of the happineſs they will enjoy in their native Land, is here repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by a moſt ſplendid and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent City, whoſe foundations are <hi>garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all manner of precious ſtones verſ.</hi> 19. Which <hi>had no need of the</hi> Sun or <hi>Moon to ſhine upon it, being inlightned by the Glory of God,</hi> ver. 23. By a Chryſtal River of Water of life <hi>proceeding from the Throne of God and of the Lamb.</hi> Chap. 22. 1. And laſtly by <hi>the Tree of life</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42839:23"/> 
                     <hi>bearing twelve manner of Fruits, yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Fruit every Month</hi> verſ. 2. All which is nothing but a Rhetorical deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the flouriſhing ſtate of the <hi>Jews</hi> after their return from Captivity. Which kind of deſcriptions were familiar to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and very frequently occurr in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetic writings ſee. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. 11, 12. 60. 19. <hi>Tob.</hi> 13. 16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="2">11. By the deſcending of the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> from God out of Heaven, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Reſtitution of the <hi>Jews</hi> by the immediate Power of God. That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the Chriſt is demonſtratively evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from their own Books, the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the old Teſtament. And yet in defiance of the moſt ſolid reaſoning and diſcourſe they have obſtinately perſiſted in their unbelief near ſeventeen hundred years. So that their Infidelity ſeems in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable by any human Methods of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. But that which to Men is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, is poſſible to God, who by the Power of his grace can reduce the moſt perverſe and incorrigible Sinners. How wonderfully and Suddenly was St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42839:24"/> converted, who of a bitter and virulent Perſecutor of Chriſtians became a moſt active and zealous Preacher of the Goſpel? Whether the Converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be wrought after the ſame manner viz, by a viſion and voice from Heaven, I cannot tell. But whatever may be the external and viſible means, the Spirit of God will be the Principal Agent in this buſineſs. Who by the internal Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their minds, with the light of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly truth, will Scatter the clouds and miſts of prejudice, and convince them of their Error and wickedneſs in rejecting the Holy <hi>Jeſus.</hi> This their repentance <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of Chap. 59. 20. Which is much clearer from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Prophecy, Rom 11. 26, 27. <hi>There ſhall come out of Sion the Deliverer, and ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from Jacob. For this is my Covenant with them, when I ſhall take away their Sins.</hi> With this agrees that of <hi>Zechary. In that day I will pour upon the houſe of Judah and the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Jeruſalem the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, and they ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:42839:24"/> 
                     <hi>ſhall Mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only Son, and ſhall be in bitterneſs for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his firſt born</hi> Chap. 12. 10. And the ſame Divine Power that worketh this inward change in the <hi>Jews,</hi> will incline the Hearts of the ſeveral Princes in whoſe Countries they are diſperſed to give them liberty of returning to the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and to furniſh them with all things needful. <hi>Surely the Iſles ſhall wait for me, and the ſhips of</hi> Tarſhiſh <hi>firſt, to bring thy Sons from far, their Silver and their Gold with them.</hi> Iſa 60. 9. Some are of Opinion that their Captivity ſhall be perpetual. But beſides that the above-mentioned text <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 24. Which ſpeaks of the diſperſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the deſolation of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Until the times of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles be fulfill'd, implies the contrary; There are ſeveral Prophecies that foretell their return. Particularly that of <hi>Amos</hi> Chap. 9. 14, 15. <hi>And I will bring again the Captivity of my People Iſrael, and they ſhall build the waſte Cities and inhabit them; and they ſhall plant vineyards, and drink the Wine thereof; they ſhall alſo make gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42839:25"/> 
                     <hi>and eat the Fruit of them. And I will plant them upon their own land, and they ſhall no more be pulled up out of their land which I have given them ſaith the Lord.</hi> The perpetuity of the Settlement here ſpoken of ſhews that it is to come, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not belong to their reeſtabliſhment after the return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> which was not of much above five hundred years conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. But no where is the preſent Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity and future return of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo clearly Propheſied of as in the Book of <hi>Tobit</hi> Chap. 14. 4, 5. <hi>Our Brethren ſhall lie ſcattered in the Earth from that good land, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhall be deſolate, and the Houſe of God in it ſhall be burned, and ſhall be deſolate for a time: And again God will have mercy on them, and bring them again into the land where they ſhall build a Temple, but not like to the firſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>till the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the age be fulfilled,</hi> which ſignifies the continuance of the ſecond Temple till the diſſolution of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Polity. And again they ſhall go into a long and great Captivity viz. the preſent, which words are wanting in the Greek and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42839:25"/> Verſions, but are in the Hebrew Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſet out by <hi>Paulus Fagius; and afterward they ſhall return from all places of their Captivity, and build up</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and the Houſe of God ſhall be built in it for ever with a glorious build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the Prophets have ſpoken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. The ſame of the <hi>Jews</hi> return be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpread over the World, Chriſtian Princes pour in their treaſures into the Holy Land, and contribute their aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances towards the rebuilding <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the reſt of the waſte and deſolate Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>The Nations of them that are ſaved, ſhall walk in the light of the New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and the Kings of the Earth do bring their Glory and Honour into it</hi> Rev 21. 24. Upon the return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> the building of the Temple and City met with great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and obſtructions from the envy and malice of the adverſaries of <hi>Judah.</hi> But now there will be no <hi>Rehums</hi> or <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballats</hi> to obſtruct their proceedings, the work will be vigorouſly carried on by the united forces and joint endeavours of <hi>Jews</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:42839:26"/> and Gentiles. This aſſiſtance of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of Chap. 60. 10, 11. <hi>The Sons of ſtrangers ſhall build up thy Walls, and their Kings ſhall miniſter unto thee; for in my wrath I ſmote thee, but in my favour have I had mercy on thee. Therefore thy Gates, ſhall be open continually, they ſhall not be ſhut day nor night, that Men may bring unto thee the forces or wealth of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, And again</hi> Chap. 61. 4, 5, 6. <hi>They ſhall build the old waſtes, they ſhall raiſe up the former deſolations, and they ſhall repair the waſte Cities, the deſolations of many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. And ſtrangers ſhall ſtand and feed your Flocks and the Sons of the Alien ſhall be your Plowmen and your Vine-dreſſers. But ye ſhall be named the Prieſts of the Lord; Men ſhall call you the Miniſters of our God; ye ſhall eat the riches of the Gentiles, and in their Glory ſhall you boaſt your ſelves.</hi> But their greateſt Glory will be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and eſtabliſhment of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion among them, with the knowledge whereof God will wonderfully inlighten their minds, for a Pattern to all the Gentile Nations profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, who ſhall now conform to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42839:26"/> Standard of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church. And this I take to be the meaning of the Nations walking in the light of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to be the full accompliſhment of theſe words in <hi>Iſaiah, the Gentiles ſhall come to thy light and Kings to the brightneſs of thy riſing Chap.</hi> 60. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:42839:27"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of</hi> Gog <hi>and</hi> Magog<hi>'s attempt againſt the Camp of the Saints.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Jews</hi> being replanted in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed land, ſhall enjoy an uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted courſe of proſperity for ſeveral a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>But when the Thouſand years of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans confinement are expired, he ſhall be looſed out of his Priſon. And ſhall go out to deceive the Nations which are in the four Quarters of the Earth, Gog and Magog, to gather them together to battel, the number of whom is as the Sand of the Sea.</hi> Rev 20. 7, 8. At whoſe inſtigation, <hi>They went up,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, on the breadth of the Earth, and compaſſed the Camp of the Saints about, and the beloved City.</hi> But this attempt ended in the total overthrow and deſtruction of that numerous Army. <hi>For fire came down from God out of Heaven, and devoured them</hi> verſ. 9. A terrible Expedition this, and no leſs aſtoniſhing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42839:27"/> than the iſſue. And that which encreaſes the Wonder is the common opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Amplitude of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which long ere this may be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be arrived at its full extent. For if all the Nations under Heaven have of a long time received and profeſſed the faith of Chriſt, as this opinion ſuppoſes 'tis very ſtrange that ſuch a prodigious number of Chriſtians from the four Quarters of the Earth, ſhould all on a ſudden con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to invade <hi>Judea</hi> and to deſtroy the <hi>Jews,</hi> profeſſing the ſame Religion, and whom their late reeſtabliſhment proclaims to be in a more peculiar manner the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>The preſent limits of the Church no doubt will be greatly enlarged by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of many Nations now ſitting in darkneſs and the ſhadow of Death. And this enlargement (whatever encreaſe it may receive in the mean time, of which there is little proſpect) may reaſonably be expected at the time of the <hi>Jews</hi> Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, from which no leſs then from their Infidelity the Gentile world will receive
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42839:28"/> great advantages. <hi>If the fall of them be the riches of the World, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing of them the riches of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; how much more their fulneſs, Rom.</hi> 11. 12. That is upon the coming in of the body of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation to the Church of Chriſt, the Goſpel will be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther propagated among the Gentiles, which is all that can be concluded from that Text. 'Tis true there are ſeveral places of Scripture which ſeem to extend the Kingdom of Chriſt over all Nations of the Earth, and to foretell the reception of the Goſpel by all People in all places of the World. Thus it is foretold of Chriſt, <hi>that there ſhould be given him Dominion and Glory and a Kingdom, that all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him, and that all Dominions ſhould ſerve and obey him,</hi> Dan. 7. 14, 27. And thus of the <hi>ſtone cut out without Hands,</hi> by which all agree is meant the Kingdom of Chriſt, it is ſaid <hi>that it became a great mountain and filled the whole Earth</hi> Dan. 2. 34, 35. But theſe and the like Prophecies ſignifie no more than the vaſt extent and largeneſs of the Chriſtian
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42839:28"/> Church in oppoſition to the ſtraitneſs of the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> which was confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the narrow limits of a ſmall Countrey. That theſe notes of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality All, Whole, are to be interpreted in a limited and reſtrained ſenſe, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from other Prophecies in this Book of <hi>Daniel</hi> concerning the extent of the Grecian and Roman Empires. For thus it is foretold of the <hi>third Kingdom that it ſhould bear Rule over all the Earth</hi> Chap. 2. 39. And of the <hi>fourth Kingdom,</hi> that <hi>it ſhould devour the whole Earth.</hi> Dan. 7. 23. And yet neither the Greeks nor Romans could pretend to an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Conqueſt of the whole World. There were ſeveral Nations never viſited by the Roman Eagle, and where the Name of <hi>Alexander</hi> was never heard of, although 'tis ſaid he was ſo vain as to weep for want of more Worlds to conquer. And thus a great part of the World will never be actually ſubject to Chriſt, nor under the government of his laws. For as the Greeks and Romans bearing Rule over and devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Earth, ſignifies no more than the greatneſs of their Conqueſts and the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42839:29"/> largeneſs of their Dominions; So by the obedience of all Nations to Chriſt, and his Kingdoms filling the whole Earth, can be meant no more than the worſhip and acknowledgment of Chriſt by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the World. And it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſying of the eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Mountain of the Lords Houſe on the top of the Mountains, and the exaltation of it above the Hills, and the Confluence of all Nations unto it</hi> Chap. 2. 2. In the next verſe the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal is changed into a particular propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>And many People ſhall go and ſay, Come ye and let us go up to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Lord, to the Houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, Intimating the reception of the Goſpel by a great part of mankind, and the continuance of the reſt of the World in the ſtate of Heatheniſm. And now the wonder of this Invaſion ceaſes. For 'tis eaſy to imagine the Camp of the Saints encompaſſed by an army of Infidels excited or provoked thereto by the Devil. But there is ſome difficulty in conceiving how this army ſhould be drawn together from ſo remote and diſtant places of the World.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42839:29"/> For the Nations of which it is compoſed are ſaid to be in the four Quarters of the Earth. But it hath been obſerved by a learned Man, that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in many places of the New Teſtament hath a Critical ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and does peculiarly refer to the Land of <hi>Judea.</hi> And in this notion it is here to be underſtood, as ſignifying not the whole World, but that Part or Portion of it, which by God was given to the Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and which is here diſtinguiſhed by a new Name, the Camp of the Saints, in alluſion to their incamping in the Wilderneſs. And then the Nations in the four Quarters or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Land will be ſome people ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Countries not far diſtant from <hi>Judea,</hi> whom we may eaſily conceive en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into a Confederacy againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and uniting their forces for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Saints of the moſt High. And thus the greateſt difficulties relating to this viſion are removed. And the plain meaning and ſignification of it appears to be the Invaſion of <hi>Judea</hi> by ſome of the neighbouring Nations. Which event if it were foretold by the Prophets, there
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42839:30"/> can be no reaſon to queſtion or doubt of the truth of this Expoſition. Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Invaſion there are ſeveral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, but the moſt remarkable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs is that in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> between which and this viſion there is an exact and admirable agreement.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Prophecy, Chap. 30.</head>
                     <p>
                        <q>In the latter days thou, <hi>viz. Gog</hi> ſhalt come into the Land that is brought back from the Sword, and is gathered out of many People, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Iſrael. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſurus montes Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelis, Junius,</hi> ver. 8. Thou ſhalt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend and come like a Storm, thou
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42839:30"/> ſhalt be like a Cloud to cover the Land, thou and all thy Bands and many People with thee, ver. 9. And it ſhall come to paſs at the ſame time, when <hi>Gog</hi> ſhall come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Lord God, that my Fury ſhall come up in my Face. And I will plead againſt him with Peſtilence and with Blood, and I will Rain upon him and his Bands, and upon the many People that are with him, an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing Rain, and great Hail-ſtones,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42839:31"/> Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, verſ. 18, 22.</q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>St. <hi>John</hi>'s Viſion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.</head>
                     <p>
                        <q>And when the Thouſand Years are expired, Satan ſhall be looſed out of his Priſon ver. 7. And ſhall go out to deceive the Nations, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Battel the number of whom is as the Sand of the Sea, verſe 8. And they went up
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42839:30"/> and compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Camp of the Saints, and the beloved City, verſ. 9.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>And Fire came down from God
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42839:31"/> out of Heaven &amp; devoured them verſ. 9.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>And whereas it is objected that <hi>Gog</hi> in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> comes out of the North parts verſ. 15. whereas <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> are ſaid to be Nations which are in the four Quarters of the Earth, this ſeeming difference admits of an eaſy Solu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For although <hi>Gog</hi> with the People of <hi>Magog</hi> came out of the North parts, yet the reſt of the people of which his army conſiſts, come from other parts. Some from <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſome from <hi>Ethiopia</hi> and <hi>Lybia,</hi> and others from the North Quarters of the leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi> viz. <hi>Gomer</hi> and <hi>Togarmah</hi> verſ. 5, 6. So that here are ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Confederacy againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and theſe lying againſt the four Corners of their Land. But whereas <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> are chief in this Expedition, therefore they only are mentioned by St. <hi>John.</hi> And for the ſame Reaſon, the judgment of God againſt this Army is in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced particularly againſt <hi>Gog.</hi> So that here is no difference but a moſt exact harmony
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42839:31"/> and conſent between the Prophet and the Divine.</p>
                     <p>But there is a farther Correſpondence as to the time of this Invaſion very remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, and which abundantly confirms my Interpretation. This in the <hi>Revelation</hi> is about a Thouſand years after the <hi>Jews</hi> Converſion, and repoſſeſſion of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Land. And that in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſucceeds the Reſtauration of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation and their Subjection to Chriſt. For in the ſeven and thirtieth Chapter is foretold the Return of the whole Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> verſ. 11, 12. The Reunion of the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms after this Return, verſ. 21, 22. And the perpetual government of <hi>David</hi> or Chriſt over them verſ. 25. And then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the next Chapter, the Prophecy of <hi>Gogs</hi> invading the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the latter days or towards the End of the World Chap. 38. 16.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:42839:32"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the general judgment and end of the World.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE laſt viſion is that of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Judgment which is the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Scene, and ends with the Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration of the World. <hi>And I ſaw a great White Throne, and him that ſat on it, from whoſe face the Earth and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no place for them. And I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God, and the Books were opened, and another Book was opened which is the Book of Life, and the Dead were judged out of thoſe things which were Written in the Books ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their works. And the Sea gave up the Dead which were in it, and Death and Hell delivered up the Dead which were in them: And they were judged every Man according to his works. And Death and Hell were caſt into the lake of fire: this is the ſecond Death. And whoſoever was not found</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:42839:32"/> 
                     <hi>Written in the Book of Life, was caſt into the lake of Fire.</hi> Rev 20. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. What St. <hi>John</hi> here ſaith of the dead ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Throne of God, and their being judged according to their works, needs not much explication. The right of judging belongs to none but God, nor is any beſides a God qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for ſo mighty a performance. But we are aſſured from Scripture that this judgment ſhall be adminiſtred by God Incarnate in the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt who is ordained the Judge of quick and Dead, Act 10. 42. For the Father judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no Man, but hath committed all judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Son, and that for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as Our Saviour himſelf tells us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the Son of Man, that is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and really Man as well as God, <hi>John</hi> 5. 27. For of the three Perſons in the Bleſſed Trinity, the Son only is perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly united to Human nature. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being God-man is the moſt proper Judge of Men who muſt be judged in their Bodies.</p>
                  <p>The conſequents of this judgment are
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42839:33"/> not ſo clear and obvious. For as for the caſting Death and Hell into the lake of Fire, with all whoſe names are not found Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of Life; and the flying away of the Earth and the Heaven from the face of him that ſits on the Throne; theſe are ſomwhat obſcure expreſſions, and not ſo eaſily underſtood,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that <hi>the laſt Enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed is Death</hi> 1 Cor 15. 26. Which deſtruction is here expreſſed by caſting Death and Hell or <hi>Hades</hi> the place of ſeparate Souls into the lake of Fire. And ſignifies that there ſhall be no more ſeperation of Soul and Body, but that Men ariſe to an immortal and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Life. But whether this immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and endleſs duration be common to all Men, or peculiar only to the Bleſſed is made matter of diſpute. That good Men ſhall live for ever in a State of unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable happineſs, is a privilege beyond the merit of the moſt perfect virtue. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life is a gift very becoming the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Goodneſs of God to beſtow. And no Man ever Quarrel'd with God on this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42839:33"/> Score, for promiſing to reward the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Services of Men with Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. But by ſome it is thought very Hard, and no way conſiſtent with the laws of juſtice, to puniſh the ſins of a ſhort life with an eternity of Torment, that Men who ſin but a few years, muſt live for ever in inſupportable Miſery, there being no proportion between Time and Eternity. This indeed is a very great difficulty, and hath inforced ſome Men to put a period to the miſeries of the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as not knowing how to reconcile the Divine Juſtice to the Eternity of Hell Torments.</p>
                  <p>Whatever is neceſſary for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Government, and ſecuring obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to laws, muſt be allowed to be juſt and lawful, Which juſtifies the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God in denouncing everlaſting mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery againſt impenitent ſinners, becauſe nothing leſs would be a ſufficient reſtraint upon moſt Men from breaking the laws of God. For if the generality of Men deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe theſe Terrors of the Lord! what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard would they have for menaces leſs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42839:34"/> ſevere? But that God ſhould execute theſe threats according to the ſtricteſt ſenſe of them, there is no neceſſity. For tho Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes oblige to a performance, yet Threats do not induce any obligation, nor does juſtice require the Execution of them. And therefore God, if he pleaſes, may deal with Sinners more mercifully than he hath threatned. But whether he will ſhew them favour, and abate any thing of the utmoſt he has denounced, I cannot tell. This is moſt certain, that no Man ſhall ſuffer beyond the juſt deſert of his actions. But who dare ſay that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in juſtice inflict Eternal puniſhment? For any Man upon ſuch a preſumption to harden himſelf againſt the clear and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs threats of endleſs Miſery, is the height of madneſs. For if at laſt the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a future ſtate are Eternal, how ſad and deplorable will his Condition be? And if they prove finite and end in his final deſtruction, yet what an ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and inſupportable thought is this, for a Man to ſuffer the pains of Hell ſo long as the Divine juſtice can inflict them, and at laſt with all ſenſe of farther ſufferings
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42839:34"/> to loſe his Being for ever. This indeed is the mildeſt fate the Sinner can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, but a much more ſevere may be his doom.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. This puniſhment of wicked Men is expreſt by being caſt into the lake of Fire. Which ſome interpret, according to the literal ſenſe, of Torment by real fire. Others underſtand this to be a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical deſcription of the unknown miſeries of the Damned. The truth ſeems divided between theſe two opinions. For firſt, it is clear from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that the Heavens and the Earth which are now, are reſerved unto fire againſt the day of judgment. 2 Ep. 3. 7. And whatever operation this fire may have upon the Apoſtate Spirits, it will doubtleſs affect the bodies of wicked Men with moſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful impreſſions.</p>
                  <p>But ſecondly, This ſeems only the Prologue to a more tragical ſtate which they muſt enter upon when this Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration is ended, and of which a lake of fire and Brimſtone is only a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42839:35"/> The miſeries of Hell are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in Scripture by the moſt ſenſible and painful things. And becauſe the moſt dreadful Idea of pain the mind can form, is the ſuffering by a raging and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire, therefore this Metaphor of fire is moſt frequently uſed. And as for the lake of Fire and Brimſtone ſo often mentioned in the Revelation, it relates to the lake <hi>Aſphaltites</hi> or the Dead Sea, the laſting Monument of thoſe ſhowrs of Fire and Brimſtone wherewith the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Theſe and the like deſcriptions are lively Images and Repreſentations of Hell Torments, and ſignifie them to be intolerable great, but they do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the true nature of them. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is in a great meaſure unknown to us, and the moſt affrighted imagination cannot reach the truth and terror of them. For who can tell or conceive what evils and Miſeries the wrath of God and his vengeance on the ungodly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. By the Earth and the Heaven
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42839:35"/> flying away from the face of him that ſits on the Throne, I underſtand the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their preſent frame. I ſee no reaſon from this or any other place of Scripture to conclude the utter Aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Annihilation of the World. The matter and Subſtance of the Earth and the reſt of the Moſaic Creation will doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs continue the ſame, but they will receive a new form, or rather be <hi>rudis indigeſtaque moles,</hi> an indigeſted heap without form or order. This Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of things St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, and tells us that this wonderful Metamorphoſis ſhall be effected by Fire, 2 Pet. 3.</p>
                  <p>Some are apt to fancy that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration of the World is in order to its refining, and that the Heavens and Earth being purged by Fire, God will erect a new World out of the old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials for the ſeat and habitation of the Bleſſed. But this is a mere Imagination and is directly contrary to Scripture, which teaches us, that the Kingdom, which the Righteous muſt inherit was prepared for them from the foundation of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42839:36"/> the World Matt. 25. 24. And as for the New Heavens and the New Earth which St. <hi>John</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeak of, I have ſhewed that they do not ſignifie the Creation of a New World after the day of Judgment, but a New ſtate of things in the old.</p>
                  <p>Others think this Conflagaation to be perpetual, and to be deſigned for the puniſhment of the wicked who ſhall live and ſuffer in this Fire to Eternnl Ages. This ſeems to have ſome foundation in Scripture, which ſpeaks of the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the wicked to everlaſting Fire. But this fire to which wicked Men will be condemned, is the ſame with that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devil and his Angels, which cannot be a Real One. For the evil Angels are ſpiritual Subſtances, and have no ſenſe of Material Impreſſinns If then the puniſhment of the Devil and wicked Men be of the ſame kind, the means and inſtrument of their Torment will not be Fire. And ſo this opinion of a burning World falls to the ground The fire therefore at the day of judgment
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42839:36"/> is not intended chiefly for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ungodly Men though they, as I ſaid before, will ſuffer by it, but for the deſtruction or diſſolution of the World, to which God will then put an end and reduce it to its Primitive Chaos. And this dark, ſpace out of which the Earth and Heaven are fled away, I ſuppoſe to be that Blackneſs of Darkneſs mentioned by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> and which is ſaid to be reſerved for the Damned. For thus of the Angels that kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habitation, St. <hi>Jude,</hi> ſaith verſ. 6. that God hath reſerved them for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Chains, or to be bound in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Chains under Darkneſs at the Judgment of the great Day, <hi>Vid. Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in Loc. Mede Diſc.</hi> 4. And the fate of ungodly Men is the ſame, for to them is likewiſe reſerved the blackneſs of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ever, verſ. 13. And in this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy State of Darkneſs and Horror, the Devil and his Angels, and all whoſe Names are not found written in the Book of Life ſhall be tormented, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure greater Miſeries than the mildeſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42839:37"/> fears and jealouſies of the moſt guilty minds can imagine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Niſi in hiſce talibus liberius paulo ſentiendi, imo &amp; errandi venia concedatur, ad profunda illa &amp; latentia veritatis adyta via nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam patefacta fuerit.</hi> Mede.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>General Titles of Books Printed for</hi> Charles Brome.</head>
            <list>
               <item>GEographical Dictionary, Fol. L'Eſtrange's Divine Offices Fol.</item>
               <item>Biſhop Wilkins Real Character, Fol.</item>
               <item>Religious Conference between a Miniſter and Pariſhioner, 4to.</item>
               <item>Satan diſrob'd from his Diſguiſe of Light, 4to.</item>
               <item>Caſe of the Quakers relating to Oaths.</item>
               <item>Blomes Hiſtory of the Bible with Cutts, 4to.</item>
               <item>L'Eſtrange, and Browns Eraſmus Colloquies, 8vo.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42839:38"/>
               <item> Colberts laſt Will and Teſtament, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Fundamental Charter of Presbytery 8vo.</item>
               <item>Sir Charles Cottons Planters, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual, 8vo.</item>
               <item>—Complete Gameſter, 8vo.</item>
               <item>—Scoffer Scoft, 8vo.</item>
               <item>—Virgils Traviſtie, 8vo.</item>
               <item>—Wonders of the Peake, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Centum Fabulae.</item>
               <item>The beſt Cutts in Octavo for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers.</item>
               <item>Earbery againſt Deiſm, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Deſdiers City and Republick of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice tranſlated out of French by Fra. Terne Gent. 8vo.</item>
               <item>St. Evremonts Caſe of the Duke and Dutcheſs of Mazarine, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Scholars Guide from the Accidence to the Univerſity, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Eſſay of Love and Marriage 12mo. Stitcht 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42839:38"/>
               <item> Portugueſe Aſia in 3 Vol. 8vo.</item>
               <item>Dr. Popes Select Novels, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Biſhop Sprats Sermons, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Plain Dealing Poulterer Stit. 8vo. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fords ſhort Catechiſm.</item>
               <item>Biſh. Wilkins Nat. Religion, 8vo.</item>
               <item>Anatomy of the Elder Tree, 12mo.</item>
               <item>Reformed Monaſtery, or the Love of Jeſus, 12mo.</item>
               <item>Seven Love Letters from a Nun to a Cavalier.</item>
               <item>Sir P. Medows Wars of Denmark, 12.</item>
               <item>Crums of Comfort 24.</item>
               <item>Godly Mans Companion 24.</item>
               <item>Guide to Heaven 24.</item>
               <item>Guide of a Chriſtian 24.</item>
               <item>Rule of Life 24.</item>
               <item>All the Pieces of the Author of the Snake in the Graſs.</item>
               <item>Biſh. Kens Expoſition on the Church Catechiſm, or the Practice of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42839:39"/>
               <item> Biſh. Kens Manual of Prayers for the uſe of the Scholars of Wincheſter College, and all other Devout Chriſtians.</item>
               <item>Biſh. Kens Sermon at the Funeral of the Lady Mary.</item>
               <item>All L'Eſtranges Tracts 4 to.</item>
               <item>Bromes Horace in Engliſh 8<hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bromes Songs 8<hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. Combers Works.</item>
               <item>Dr. Combers Catechiſm.</item>
               <item>Chriſtian Education of Children ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Maxims of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, and the Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Fathers of the Church, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:42839:39"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
